<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the parish-church of St Nicholas, in the city of Bristol, August the 27th, 1691 Being the anniversary festival of the natives of that city. By Thomas Cary, M.A. and vicar of the parish of St Philip and Jacob, in the city of Bristol.</title>
            <author>Cary, Thomas, 1648 or 9-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C743BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897405</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2492:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the parish-church of St Nicholas, in the city of Bristol, August the 27th, 1691 Being the anniversary festival of the natives of that city. By Thomas Cary, M.A. and vicar of the parish of St Philip and Jacob, in the city of Bristol.</title>
                  <author>Cary, Thomas, 1648 or 9-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Wall, bookseller in Bristol,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XII, 15 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135575:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> NICHOLAS,</hi> IN THE City of BRISTOL, <hi>August</hi> the 27th, 1691. BEING The ANNIVERSARY FESTIVAL OF THE <hi>Natives of that City.</hi> By <hi>THOMAS CARY,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of the Pariſh of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Philip and Jacob,</hi> in the City of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Wall,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Briſtol.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135575:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135575:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful Sir <hi>John Dudelſtone,</hi> Kt. PRESIDENT: THE OFFICERS, And the Reſt of the SOCIETY OF THE NATIVES OF THE City of BRISTOL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Countrymen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Diſcourſe which had lately your Audience, now offers itsſelf to your View, it was compoſed for you, and doth by Right belong to you. The Deſign of it is,
<pb facs="tcp:135575:3"/> by beating down the Price of the World, to perſwade you to make ſuch a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of it, while you live in it, that you may go out of it with comfort. GOD hath bleſſed many of you with ample Eſtates, it is your Duty to return him a Tributary Acknowledgment by a Generous Charity: That theſe Meditations may be ſerviceable for this End, is the hearty Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Countrymen, </salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, THOMAS CARY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135575:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LUKE xij. xv.</bibl> And he ſaid unto them, Take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs: for a man's life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE occaſion of theſe words, was an improper Petition preſented to our bleſſed Lord, by one who came to hear his Doctrine, while he was diſcourſing on a Divine Subject, a certain Worldling who minded Earth more than Heaven, interrupted him with this unſeaſonable addreſs: <hi>Maſter, ſpeak to my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he divide the inheritance with me,</hi> verſ. 13. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, apprehending Chriſt to be the promiſed Meſſiah, and miſtaking the Meſſiah (as the Jews generally did) to be a Temporal Prince, he deſired him to exerciſe his Authority in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour (whoſe Kingdom is not of this World) would not invade the Office of the Civil Magiſtrate, or intermeddle with Matters Forreign to his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>He ſaid unto him, who made me a judge, or a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der over you?</hi> verſ. 14.</p>
            <p>The Son of God came not from Heaven to ſettle Mens Eſtates, but to ſave their Souls; he was not ſent to be an Arbitrator in our Worldly Concerns, but to execute the Office of a Mediator between God and Man; not to compoſe Differences about Temporal
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135575:4"/> Rights, but to reconcile GOD to Man, and Man to GOD.</p>
            <p>However, our bleſſed Lord, who improved all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing good, takes advantage from hence to ſtrike at the Root from whence this Interruption grew; he doth not directly fall on the Perſon who diſturbed him in his Diſcourſe, but obliquely reflects on the cauſe of it. The Covetouſneſs of this Man's Heart indiſpoſed him to attend to our Saviour's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and therefore our bleſſed Lord cautions the whole Auditory againſt this ſin: <hi>And he ſaid unto them, Take heed and beware of covetouſneſs: for a man's life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain theſe two Particulars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. A Caution: <hi>Take heed and beware of covetouſneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. An Argument to enforce it: <hi>For a man's life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I. A Caution: <hi>Take heed and beware of covetouſneſs.</hi> Covetouſneſs is an inordinate deſire of worldly Riches; the Root from whence this and all other Vices grow, is evil Concupiſcence in the Heart, Senſual Luſt receives diſtinct Names from its different Objects; if Honour be its Object, it is then called Ambition; if Pleaſure, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs; if Riches, Covetouſneſs, or to uſe the Apoſtle's Expreſſion, <hi>The love of money,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 10.</p>
            <p>All deſire of worldly Riches is not Covetouſneſs, Men muſt labour in their Callings, be provident in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135575:4"/> and lay up for their Families: Induſtry is not Sin but Duty. To increaſe an Eſtate by honeſt means and endeavours, is ſo far from being culpable, that it is a ſingular commendation; but the deſire of worldly Riches is then ſinful, when it is immoderate, and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Love of the World exceeds its proper bounds, it is the Sin of Covetouſneſs. Let us then conſider in what caſes the deſire of Temporal Things is immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and then we ſhall find out the Nature of this Sin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The deſire of Riches is immoderate, when the World alienates our Hearts from God and our Duty; when we love the World more than God, prefer Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal before Spiritual Riches, labour more for our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies than our Souls, and for the World neglect God's Service, and our Etenral Concerns, then we are guilty of the Sin of Covetouſneſs; ſuch a love of the World is inconſiſtent with the love of God: <hi>No man can ſerve two maſters, for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or elſe he will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ye cannot ſerve God and mammon,</hi> Matth. 6. 24. <hi>Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world: If any man love the world, the love of the father is not in him: for all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye; and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15, 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The deſire of Riches is immoderate, when Men uſe unjuſt means to enrich themſelves, when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change their Souls for the World, and have ſo ſeared their Conſciences as to uſe Fraud, Perjury, Oppreſſion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135575:5"/> or any other diſhoneſt Practices to increaſe their Eſtates. All theſe unlawful Methods are Evidences of a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Heart.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The deſire of Riches is immoderate, when it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts the Mind with perplexing Cares: Exceſſive Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows for the Loſſes and Diſappointments Men meet with in their worldly Concerns, rebellious Murmurings againſt the Providence of the Almighty, Envyings and Repinings at the Proſperity of our Neighbours, anxious and diſquieting Thoughts concerning Futurity, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing Fears about the Events of our Endeavours, are certain Indications of the Sin of Covetouſneſs; it is in Scripture oppoſed to Contentment of Mind in every ſtate of Life, and a ſecure Confidence in the All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of God: <hi>Let your converſation be without cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs; and be content with ſuch things as ye have: for he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13. 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The deſire of Riches is immoderate, when it is inconſiſtent with the Graces of Charity, Mercifulneſs, and Liberality. He that hath not a Heart to give to the Poor, when God furniſheth him with means and opportunities, is a covetous Man.</p>
            <p>The Covetous love the World above all, purſue it with Violence, ſtick not at any Methods to attain their Ends, imploy it to bad purpoſes, keep it with trouble, and loſe it with deſpair.</p>
            <p>Having thus explained the Nature of this Sin, I come now to diſcover the Evil of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Covetouſneſs is an idolatrous departure from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135575:5"/> All-ſufficient Creator, to the inſufficient Creature. Whatſoever a Man ſets his Heart moſt on, labours moſt for, ſpends the greateſt part of his time in queſt of, delights moſt in, truſts moſt to, and values him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt upon, that is his God: the ambitious Man's God is Honour, the Epicure's Pleaſure, the Gluttons the Belly, and the Covetous Man's Riches; the World is the Idol he adores, becauſe the gain of it is his ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end; therefore the Apoſtle calls <hi>Covetouſneſs Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> Col. 3. 5.</p>
            <p>The Covetous Man's Heart is wholly departed from the Lord; with the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> he forſakes the true God, to worſhip a Golden Calf; with thoſe in the Parable of the Goſpel-Banquet, he prefers his Farm or his Merchandize before his God and Saviour; he knows no God but Gain, no Paradiſe but an earthly Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; Bonds and Mortgages from Men, are with him of greater Value, and a better Security than the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Promiſes of God; give him Earth here, he cares not for Heaven hereafter, neither will he part with an Eſtate in hand, for the Kingdom of Glory in reverſion. The Rich Man in the Goſpel could boaſt much of his Morality, yet he had not learnt ſo much Self-denial: <hi>Go thy way</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſell whatſoever thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in heaven: but he was ſad at that ſaying, and went away grieved, for he had great poſſeſſions,</hi> Mark 10. 21. Our bleſſed Lord took occaſion from hence, to declare the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Salvation to thoſe that are covetous, by propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning it to the paſſage of a Camel thro' a Needle's
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135575:6"/> eye: <hi>How hard is it for them that trust in riches to enter into the kingdom of God? It is eaſier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God,</hi> verſ. 24, 25.</p>
            <p>The Covetous Man's Practices demonſtrate the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of his Heart; he is always laying up on Earth, becauſe he believes not that there is an Heaven; his reſtleſs purſuit after Temporal Riches, is an argument he expects no other Satisfaction than what this World can afford; his continual Labour for the Body, is an evidence he thinks his Soul ſhall die with it; he that believes in earneſt that he hath an immortal Spirit to be happy or miſerable for-ever, will not wholly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his better part, and lay out all his care on that which muſt periſh; the Covetous Man would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God for the World, did he not apprehend to be a greater Good: Mammon is the only Maſter he ſerves, Worldly Gain the only Good he deſires, and Worldly Loſs the only Evil he fears.</p>
            <p>Covetouſneſs incapacitates the Heart to perform any Religious Duty after a Spiritual Manner: How can he pray devoutly, whoſe Heart is devoted to the World? How can he profitably hear the Word of God, whoſe Ears are never attentive but to the Sound of Gain? whoſe Thoughts are on his Worldly Affairs? No! <hi>the care of this world, and the deceitfulneſs of riches, choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful,</hi> Mat. 13. 22. The moſt Divine Diſcourſes can no more affect his Heart, than the moſt Melodious Muſick doth the Ear of a Beaſt. When our Saviour exhorted to Charity, <hi>the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135575:6"/> Phariſees who were covetous heard all theſe things, and they derided him,</hi> Luke 16. 14. How can he value the love and favour of God, the Language of whoſe Heart is, Let my Corn and Wine increaſe, and let God lift up the Light of his Countenance upon whom he pleaſe? How can he bleſs God for his Mercies, whoſe unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heart is not ſatisfied with too much, but always ravenous after more? God and the World are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in their Natures that both cannot have our Hearts, the love of the one, doth imply a contempt of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it remains therefore, that a Covetous Man is a profane and graceleſs Perſon, without God in the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Covetouſneſs is an Argument of a baſe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Nature: It lodgeth only in narrow Souls, and earthly Spirits, a generous Mind diſdains to entertain this filthy Luſt; the Covetous Man acts from and for Self, he is unprofitable both to Church and State, and uſeleſs in every relation; he hath not a Heart to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Publick Good before his Private Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Of all Perſons in Humane Societies, the Covetous are moſt unfit for Publick Offices. How unqualified are they for the Power of Judicature, who never want Hearts, when they have Opportunities of taking Bribes? Covetouſneſs perverts Juſtice either from fear of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſome great Perſonage, or from hope to oblige him. To what baſe Flatteries; to what ſervile Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances; to what ſlaviſh Drudgeries, doth this Vice expoſe Men? That Mind cannot be free and ingenious which is inſlaved with the Love of Money: Magiſtracy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135575:7"/> is never more diſgraced than when miſplaced on Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Men; this ſin is inconſiſtent with that State and Grandeur that ſhould keep up the Honour of it: exact Juſtice, and a generous Charity tend more to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it from Contempt, than all the Enſigns of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Liberality, and Hoſpitality, render it more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable than Swords and Maces, or a tedious Train of Attendants; and therefore <hi>Jethro</hi> adviſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to provide for Magiſtrates, <hi>Able men, ſuch as fear God: men of truth, hating covetouſneſs,</hi> Exod. 18. 21.</p>
            <p>The Covetous Man is at the beſt but a Slave in a Mine of Ore, a Captive in Fetters of Gold, the Jaylor, rather than the Injoyer of his Eſtate: This Vice bows down the Soul towards the Earth, hinders its flight to Things above, and eclipſeth it, by interpoſing the World between it and Heaven.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſin was Pride, this caſt Angels out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; the next to that, was an Affectation to be as Gods, to know Good and Evil; this caſt our firſt Parents out of Paradiſe; theſe ſins are very great, and cannot be ſufficiently aggravated; but they were ſins of a more generous nature than this of Covetouſneſs; they aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be greater than they were, but the Covetous Man debaſeth and leſſeneth himſelf; they would have raiſed themſelves higher towards Heaven, but the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Man ſtoops lower towards the Earth, as if he lay under the Curſe of the Serpent, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thy belly ſhalt thou go, and duſt ſhalt thou eat all the days of thy life,</hi> Gen. 3. 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Covetouſneſs is a moſt cruel and unnatural Vice:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135575:7"/> It fills the Head with Cares, the Heart with Sorrows, and the Mind with Fears; What diſcontents at Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; what melancholy damps; what excruciating thoughts do torture the Minds of Covetous Men? Covetouſneſs is a ſin and a puniſhment together, a Vulture in the Heart, a Wolf in the Breaſt, a Serpent in the Boſome, it oppreſſeth the Spirits, drieth up the Radical moiſture, depauperates the Blood, degradeth the Soul, and conſumes the Body: a Covetous Man ſtarves at a Plentiful Table, thirſts in Rivers of Water, and is poor in the midſt of abundance; he lives in want of what he hath, and in this is moſt miſerable, that he only knows the Cares and Sorrows, not the Comforts of being Rich: <hi>For what hath a man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart wherein he hath laboured under the ſun? For all his days are ſorrows, and his travel grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 22, 23. Nature is contented with a little, but the cravings of a Covetous Mind are bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; Rivers of Potable Gold will not quench this Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropick Thirſt, Crowns heaped up to Heaven cannot ſatisfie this Ambition; Contentment renders little much, but Covetouſneſs makes much but a little.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Covetouſneſs is a ſin of prodigious folly: Were it lawful to make Satyrs and Invectives againſt any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, it would be againſt the Covetous; their Vices may be expoſed to ſhame and contempt, although their Perſons ought to be pitied; For what folly is it to hoard up that with care and ſorrow, which is good for nothing but to be enjoyed? Or to ſweat and labour
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135575:8"/> all our Lives for thoſe things we muſt leave for ever in a moment? What an unprofitable bargain is it, to gain a tranſitory World, with the loſs of an immortal Soul? What madneſs to render our Lives uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, by denying our ſelves thoſe Bleſſings God hath plentifully given us to make them comfortable?</p>
            <p>We laugh at Children when we ſee them fond of gaudy Rattles, and gilded Trifles; the Covetous Man doth act the Child's folly in a higher Sphear, he is taken with Gold, not for its uſe, but for the value the World hath put on it, he admires it more for its luſter, than its convenience; it is only the fancy that giveth ſuch a great worth to this Metal; were it not for Cuſtom, a Barr of Iron would be as precious as a Wedge of Gold: where Shells are uſed for Money, they are as ſerviceable as Plate is among us. Gold and Silver are of no other uſe, than as they ſerve to purchaſe the Neceſſaries and Conveniences of Life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are never to be deſired for their own ſakes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Covetouſneſs is the root of all evil: The School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men reckon up ſeven Branches growing from this Prolifick Root, <note place="margin">Aq. 2da. 2dae quaes 118.</note> 
               <hi>Treachery, Fraud, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, Perjury, Diſcontent, Violence, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmercifulneſs.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>They that will be rich fall into temptation, and a ſnare, and many fooliſh and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition: for the love of money is the root of all evil; which while ſome have coveted after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves through with many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 9, 10.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135575:8"/>
            <p>I ſhall briefly enumerate the principal Vices that do neceſſarily attend Covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1. Uncharitableneſs.</label> Covetouſneſs makes Men hard hearted, cruel; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of the Miſeries of others; the greateſt Objects of Pity, make no impreſſion on their Affections, their Ears are deaf to the moſt clamorous Neceſſities, the Tears of Widows and Orphans affect not their obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Hearts; where this ſin reigns, there is always a ſavage, barbarous, and unmerciful Nature.</p>
            <p>He whoſe whole work it is to heap up, will not ſpare any thing: So far are the Covetous from ſupplying the Poor, that it is well if they do not oppreſs them; the rich Glutton in the Parable, would not afford ſo much as the Crumbs his Dogs did eat, to poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he found more mercy from the Dogs that licked him, than from their Covetous Maſter. Churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> ſurfeited himſelf, but denied Food in extremity to <hi>David</hi> and his Company: the hands of a covetous Man are never open to give, but to receive.</p>
            <p>The Uncharitableneſs of Covetous Men is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Infidelity of their Hearts; God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to give to the Poor; he ſends daily Objects to the Doors of the Rich, and hath promiſed to reward Charity both in this Life, and that to come, but the Covetous do not believe a promiſing God, or will not take his Word; they prefer a ſmall Intereſt on Earth, before Bags that wax not old, Treaſures that fail nor, a Hundred-fold in this life, and in the World to come life everlaſting.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135575:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>2. Oppreſſion.</label> The Covetous Man meaſures Good and Evil by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and Loſs; Juſt and Unjuſt are, with him, but vain Notions, Right and Wrong are with him, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant words. Whence come Rapine and Violence, Oppreſſion of poor Neighbours, Invaſion of other Mens Rights, breach of Contracts, litigious Suits of Law, ſecret Underminings of one another, falſe Weights and Ballances, fraudulent Bargains, come they not from Mens covetous Hearts? The Covetous Man foreſtals the Market, ingroſſeth the Bleſſings of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts the largeneſs of his immenſe Bounty; his Coffers are the bottomleſs Pit, wherein the unmeaſurable Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God is loſt; his Barns are full, when the Poor want Bread to ſtop their Mouths from Complaints.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3. Inhumanity.</label> When this ſin grows predominant, it makes Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural in denying themſelves the Conveniences of Life; ſometimes they ſtarve their Families while they live, that they may leave them rich when they die; the Curſe of God is on ſuch covetous Perſons, he judicially ſuffers them to be infatuated by this baſe Luſt, or elſe they could not be ſo cruel to Themſelves and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. <hi>Then I returned and ſaw vanity under the ſun: there is one alone, and there is not a ſecond: yea, he hath neither child nor brother; yet there is no end of all his labour; neither is his eye ſatisfied with riches; neither ſaith he, for whom do I labour, and bereave my ſoul of good? this is alſo vanity, yea it is a ſore travel,</hi> Eccl. 4. 7, 8. So again, <hi>There is an evil that I have ſeen under the ſun, and it is common among men: a man to whom God
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135575:9"/> hath given riches, wealth, and honour: ſo that he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing for his ſoul of all that he deſireth, yet God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him not power to eat thereof; but a ſtranger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil diſeaſe,</hi> Eccl. 6. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>4. Many Doctrinal and Practical Errors ſpring from Covetouſneſs. This impure Luſt blinds the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and clouds the judging Faculty; he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the due exerciſe of his Reaſon, who is addicted to an immoderate love of worldly things; the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is biaſſed to believe thoſe Doctrines to be true, and thoſe Practices good, which tend to our Temporal Intereſts, be they never ſo falſe and evil, when Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs prevails in the heart. <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That while ſome coveted after money, they erred from the faith, 1 Tim. 6. 5. St. Peter hath foretold, That there ſhall be falſe teachers, who privily ſhall bring in damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction: and many ſhall follow their pernicious ways, by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of: and through covetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make merchandize of you, 2 Pet. 2. 1, 2.</hi> They are farther deſcribed: <hi>Having an heart exerciſed with covetous practices, and loving the wages of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> verſ. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>For an inſtance of this, we need go no farther than the preſent Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> many erroneous Doctrines, and unchriſtian Practices among the Papiſts were firſt invented, and are ſince maintained to gratifie the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires of their Clergy: their pretended Supremacy, Infallibility, Purgatory; their Canonization of Saints,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135575:10"/> Jubilees, Pilgrimages, Prayers for the Dead; Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Diſpenſations flowed from this Spring: theſe Doctrines have no foundation either in Revelation or Reaſon; they tend only to ſupport the external glory and greatneſs of that Church; and they are fond of them for the ſame reaſon that <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and the Crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were of <hi>Diana,</hi> and her Silver Shrines: <hi>Sirs, ye know, that by this craft we have our wealth,</hi> Act. 19, 25.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Church by ſelling Indulgences for paſt Sins, and Diſpenſations for Sins to come; and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Maſſes to ſale, to deliver Souls out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, appears to be the Myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> mentioned in the Revelation of <hi>St. John;</hi> for this Church only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the Character of trading in the <hi>ſouls of men,</hi> Rev. 18. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <label>6. Covetouſneſs is a damnable Sin.</label> St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſſwades the <hi>Corinthians</hi> from having any ſociety with a covetous Brother: <hi>If any one that is called a brother be covetous, with ſuch an one, No! not to eat, 1 Cor. 5. 11.</hi> And he rangeth the <hi>Covetous</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe <hi>that ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 10. Covetouſneſs is inconſiſtent with a ſtate of Grace, and therefore muſt be mortified before we can attain to a ſtate of Salvation. He who is fond of this viſible World is unprepared for the inviſible; How unfit are they to live in a World of pure Spirits, who mind only earthly things? Our Souls muſt be weaned from this World, and live above it, before they can be qualified for a better; a contempt of this by a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Heavenly-mindedneſs, muſt train us up for that. In Heaven there are no Houſes or Lands, Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135575:10"/> Food or Rayment, and therefore a ſenſual World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling could not take any pleaſure in it: there are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual riches, intellectual Delights, holy Pleaſures, there is not one thing proper for the animal life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtate of it doth not ſuit a carnal Soul. He who here reliſheth no Pleaſures but thoſe of ſence, ſhall not only loſe that World he was fondly taken with, but alſo be condemned to a World of unſpeakable Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where he ſhall curſe his Folly for giving away his Soul for this.</p>
            <p>2. An Argument to enforce the Caution, <hi>Take heed and beware of covetouſneſs: for a man's life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Senſus est admodum popularis, vitam non juvari ex eo quòd quis plus in bonis habeat quàm ſatis ſit ad naturae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideria:</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi> upon the Text; that is, the ſence is very obvious, a Man's Life is not ſupported by thoſe things which are more than will ſuffice to ſatisfie the Deſires of Nature, no Man hath truly any more than he enjoys of the good things of this life, Water in the Brook quencheth not the Thirſt, Corn in the Barn ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth not Hunger, Gold in the Bag ſupplieth not our Neceſſities, Nature is preſerved, the Body comforted by thoſe things we uſe and enjoy, not by thoſe we keep and poſſeſs, a moderate portion of the good things of this Life is enough for uſe and enjoyment, and therefore we may be happy without abundance; the comfort and conveniency of Life doth not conſiſt in abundance, but in a competency, and therefore we ſhould not covet more than enough; Superfluities are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135575:11"/> more than we can uſe, and why ſhould we fondly deſire them? Worldly Riches are deſirable, not for their own ſakes, but for the purpoſes and conveniences of life, and therefore we have enough of them, when we have as much as we can uſe and enjoy.</p>
            <p>That the happineſs of Humane Life doth not conſiſt in the abundance of worldly things, I ſhall evince by theſe following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Abundance of worldly things is unneceſſary: The happineſs of life conſiſts in a ſufficiency, not in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities, we may live very comfortably with a little, and miſerably with much, Nature is ſatisfied with a competency of Food and Rayment, and Happineſs conſiſts in the ſatisfaction of our natural Deſires, not in gratifying our extravagant Luſts; Nature is eaſily ſatisfied, but Luſt never; a Seemleſs Coat will keep us as warm as a Princely Robe, Water quencheth the Thirſt better than Wine, Sleep is as ſweet in a Cottage, as in a Palace, plain Food ſatisfieth Hunger, and is more wholeſome than delicious Meats: rich Apparel, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Wines, ſtately Houſes, and ſplendid Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſerve only to gratifie <hi>the lust of the fleſh, the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life:</hi> and therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur</hi> a Man much celebrated for his Wiſdom, prefers a Competency before either of the Extreams, Riches or Poverty: <hi>Give me neither poverty nor riches, feed me with food convenient for me,</hi> Prov. 30. 8. If the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of life conſiſted in abundance, then all that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound would be happy, but every day's experience convinceth us of the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135575:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. Abundance of worldly things cannot ſatisfie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous deſires. Nature hath Bounds, Luſt none; the World hath Limits, Covetouſneſs is unmeaſurable: The Riches of both the <hi>Indies</hi> tranſported hither, would not content a covetous Heart: this Luſt is as unſatiable as Hell and the Grave, he that is not ſatisfied with a competency, neither would he be with abundance: <hi>He that loveth ſilver, ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver; nor he that loveth abundance, with increaſe: this is alſo vanity,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 10.</p>
            <p>God hath given us infinite Deſires, that we might direct them towards an infinite Good; he made the Soul of Man uncapable of ſatisfaction but from an infinite Good; it is God's Royal Prerogative that he alone can ſatisfie an immortal Spirit; when we direct our infinite Deſires to God, we purſue our proper ſatisfaction, and when we are united with God we attain it, then our Deſires are terminated; we imploy them for that Noble End they were intended, and attain that infinite Good which was deſigned for them; but when we turn our Deſires after worldly things, they cannot meet with any ſatisfaction; the reaſon is, becauſe there is no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the Subject and the Object; the World, though it be very large, yet it is but finite, and a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite World can no more ſatisfie infinite Deſires, than a drop can contain the Ocean: again, the Soul being an immortal Spirit, whatſoever ſatisfies it muſt run paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with its duration; but the whole World muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be diſſolved, and the Earth, and all the Works that are therein muſt be burnt; How then can a periſhing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135575:12"/> World ſatisfie an immortal Soul, that muſt ſurvive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely the duration of it? It remains therefore, that the Soul cannot be ſatisfied, but by an infinite and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Good; it may make many vain Experiments, but is never at reſt, till it fix upon its proper Center God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Abundance of worldly things expoſeth to great Temptations and Troubles. Great Eſtates are gained many times with the loſs of the Soul, more valuable than the whole viſible World; they that have them are ſubject to immoderate Cares, and liable to great Diſappointments: <hi>When goods increaſe, they are increaſed that eat them: And what good is there to the owners there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſaving the beholding of them with their eyes? The ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſleep. There is a ſore evil which I have ſeen under the ſun; namely, riches kept for the owners thereof, to their hurt,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Crowns have Thorns as well as Jewels in them, a glorious Scepter is alſo weighty, Magiſtracy itsſelf is but an honourable Burthen; Great Men are liable to the Envy of Great Perſons; whoſoever ſits upon the higheſt Pinacle of worldly Honour, is in this more miſerable than the meaneſt, that he is liable to a greater fall. Contentment is oftner found in a Cottage, than in a Palace; Quietneſs is oftner cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Rags than Robes; Worldly Pomp and Grandeur, only make it poſſible to be more extreamly Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; Happineſs is more in Solitude and Retirement from the buſie World, than in the crouded Courts of Kings.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135575:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Agur</hi> had much reaſon on his ſide, when he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Competency before either of the Extreams; he deprecated Riches, leaſt <hi>being full he ſhould deny God, and ſay, Who is the Lord? and poverty; least he ſhould ſteal, and take the name of his God in vain,</hi> Prov. 30. 9.</p>
            <p>He deſired rather to ſteer a middle Courſe, or to be placed in a middle Station, than to run the hazard of either of the Extreams; certainly he who is bleſſed with a competent Portion of the good Things of this Life, and hath a holy Soul in a healthy Body, is the happieſt Man on Earth; he is not ſeated on the top of the Mountain ſo as to fear a Storm, nor in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Vally ſo as to fear an Inundation, he is not ſo high as to be afraid of a Fall, nor ſo low as to be trampled on; he is not ſo great as to attract envy, nor ſo little as to provoke contempt; he hath enough to maintain him while he lives, and to bury him when he is dead. Again: Abundance expoſeth Men to many deſtructive Luſts; Riches betray Men to Pride, Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Senſuality, Ambition, and Contempt of God and Religion; the Rich are careful and troubled about many things, and neglect the one thing needful; they ſeldom think of God, their Souls, the inviſible World, and a Future Account, becauſe they are well pleaſed to continue here; the Pleaſures of this World benumb the Powers of the Soul, exalt Senſual Appetite; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Way to Heaven more difficult, and dull Men aſleep in a Carnal Security.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Abundance of worldly things is of little uſe to the Soul: They ſerve only for the purpoſes of the Body,
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:135575:13"/> be joyful in the day of proſperity: Religion allows innocent Mirth, and ſober Feſtivals: <hi>It is good and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for one to eat and drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the ſun all the days of his life, which God giveth him, for it is his portion: every man alſo to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to rejoyce in his labour, this is the gift of God,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>But then God's Bleſſing muſt go with the uſe of the Creatures, elſe they cannot render Life happy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable; he is truly rich, who hath God's Bleſſing on all that he hath, whether he hath much or little: <hi>A little that a righteous man hath, is better than the riches of many wicked, Pſal. 37. 16. The bleſſing of the Lord it maketh rich, and he addeth no ſorrow with it, Prov. 10. 22. There is that ſcattereth, and yet increaſeth: and there is that with-holdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty, Prov. 11. 24.</hi> When <hi>Daniel</hi> had only Pulſe to eat, and Water to drink, yet becauſe God bleſſed his Meals, <hi>his countenance appeared fairer and fatter in fleſh, than all the children which did eat the portion of the King's meat, Dan. 1. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The happineſs of Humane Life conſiſts in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of our ſelves, and all that we have to God.</p>
            <p>Then we are truly happy, when we are fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Providence and All-ſufficiency of God, are the Objects of his peculiar Care, and can entirely give up our ſelves to his wiſe Conduct. The only way to ſatisfie our deſires, is to keep them within bounds: the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135575:13"/> only way to have our own wills, is to make God's will our will; he that deſires nothing but what pleaſeth God, always obtains what he deſires; it is not poſſible to bring up worldly things to our carnal deſires; but we may by the aſſiſtance of divine Grace bring down our deſires to our preſent Enjoyments thus did <hi>St. Paul, I have learned in whatſoever ſtate I am, therewith to be content: I know both how to be abaſed, and I know how to abound: every-where, and in all things I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, both to be full, and to be hungry, both to abound, and to ſuffer need: I can do all things through Christ that ſtrengtheneth me, Phil. 4. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An unſanctified heart is unſatiable, and he that hath unſatiable deſires can never be happy, becauſe he can never obtain his deſires. Self-will oppoſeth God's will, and ſo can never be ſatisfied, becauſe God's will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts it; and his will muſt be done, whether we will or not; God's will over-rules all, and then we obtain our wills, when they are ſubjected to the will of God. When God gave the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Manna from Heaven, they were not contented with Angels Food, they murmured againſt his Providence; an evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that Bread from Heaven will not ſtop the mouth of an unſanctifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Man from murmuring againſt God; the unholy, are always unthankful.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe God ſhould ſpread before us all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the World, and give us liberty to take what we would, could we do better than to refer our ſelves to the All-wiſe God, and deſire him to chuſe for us? If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be All-ſufficient, Wiſe, Good, and Faithful,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135575:14"/> we muſt conclude him to be fitteſt to diſtribute to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man his Portion; we cannot be better provided for, becauſe he knows what is moſt convenient for us, we cannot be more ſecure, than under the guidance of infinite Wiſdom; to acquieſce in the will of <hi>God,</hi> is to diſcharge ourſelves of all troubleſome thoughts, becauſe it is to caſt all our care on him who careth for us: the inſufficient Creature is then moſt ſelf-ſufficient, when it goes out of Self into the All-ſufficient Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; Self is a vain Idol, that deceives all that depend on it, <hi>God</hi> is an all-ſufficient <hi>Good</hi> to all that rely on him, an unreſerved Reſignation of our ſelves to <hi>God,</hi> is the great ground of true Content, every Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Providence is welcome to him who believes, that all good and evil things come from his hand, and ſubmits his will to the will of <hi>God;</hi> a will reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to <hi>God,</hi> doth not only ſubmit to him by a paſſive Patience, but actively concur with his Providence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that ſtate of Life to be beſt, which <hi>God</hi> judgeth fitteſt. When we have this Principle of Contentment within our ſelves, our hearts are at reſt, we are ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the preſent, and may cheerfully rely on <hi>God</hi> for the future; we are then prepared for every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Life; becauſe he whoſe will is ſwallowed up in the will of <hi>God,</hi> doth always chooſe what <hi>God</hi> ſends: it ſweetens Afflictions, mitigates Sorrows, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Joys; when we can command our deſires, a little will ſerve to render this Life comfortable; in ſhort, we cannot be happy without content; we cannot be content, unleſs we have our wills; we cannot have our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135575:14"/> wills, any other way, than by making GOD's will our will, and therefore without a hearty reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves to God, Humane Life cannot be happy.</p>
            <p>3. The happineſs of Humane Life conſiſts in doing good. Riches are good or evil, as the Man is that enjoys them, they are not laudably good, or criminally evil in themſelves; but we make them good or evil by our management of them; they are never to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but for thoſe uſes for which they were intended; in a good Man's hands they afford means and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of acting many excellent Vertues, as Charity, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, and Hoſpitality; in a wicked Man's hands they are but the Vigour of Vice, the Fuel of Luſt, the Snates of the Devil, at the beſt but a Talent wrapt up in a Napkin.</p>
            <p>Let us make a good uſe of <hi>God's</hi> Bleſſings, and then we ſhall be happy here and hereafter. The end of life is to do good, all comfortable Reflections come from good Actions; good Works juſtifie our Faith, Charity to the Poor will ſanctifie the Bleſſings of <hi>God</hi> to us, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do better, than in giving to <hi>God</hi> what he hath boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully given us, this is to make an Offering to <hi>God,</hi> of what others make an Idol. To do good is to imitate the higheſt Perfection; to be Benefactors to the Poor, is to reſemble our heavenly Father: <hi>But love ye your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again, and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the children of the highest: for he is kind to the unthankful, and to the evil: be ye therefore merciful, as your Father alſo is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135575:15"/> merciful,</hi> Luke 6. 35. It is the Character of Chriſt the Son of <hi>God,</hi> That <hi>he went about doing good:</hi> let us imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him, as <hi>we have opportunity in doing good unto all men, eſpecially unto them who are of the houſhold of faith: to do good, and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> Heb. 13. 16.</p>
            <p>The more good we do, the more peace ſhall we have in our own Souls, the more favour with <hi>God,</hi> the more comfort when we reflect on our paſt Lives, the more aſſurance of Heaven when we come to die, and the greater reward in glory unto all eternity: <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high-minded, nor trust in uncertain riches, but in the living God, who giveth us richly all things to enjoy: that they do good, and that they be rich in good works, ready to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute, willing to communicate, laying up in ſtore for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a good foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>To do good, is to live up to that Noble End for which we were born, and to act according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of our Beings. He who comes into the World, and goes out of it again without doing any good, is born in vain, and may be reckoned rather among the dead than the living; yea, he is as uſeleſs as if he had never been.</p>
            <p>Riches are a Talent committed to our charge by <hi>God,</hi> he expects we ſhould imploy this Talent to good Uſes. The Rich are <hi>God's</hi> Almoners whom he hath choſen to diſtribute his Bounty. He gave not Riches that Men ſhould ruſt in Idleneſs, and ſurfeit with Luxury,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135575:15"/> but that we might have opportunities of doing good. Nothing can procure a greater Reputation either with <hi>God</hi> or Man, than Charity to the Poor; to build an Alms-houſe is the beſt way to perpetuate our Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; Liberality commands Honour and Reſpect; the only lawful way to grow Popular, is to keep an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitable Table; to cloath the Naked, is to give the richeſt Livery; to ſeed the Hungry, to give drink to the Thirſty, to viſit Priſoners, and redeem Captives, is a glorious and <hi>God</hi>-like Work.</p>
            <p>Doing good doth affect the Mind with rational Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, it is a degree of Heaven to look back upon a Life full of good Works; a reflection upon a good Action is as grateful to the Soul, as Meat to an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Stomach: It was <hi>Job's</hi> Comfort in his Adverſity, that he was charitable in his Proſperity: <hi>I delivered the poor that cried, and the fatherleſs, and him that had none to help him. The bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh came upon me, and I cauſed the windows heart to ſing for joy: I was eyes to the blind, and feet was I to the lame, I was a father to the poor,</hi> Job 29. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>When <hi>God</hi> had finiſhed the Works of his Creation, he reſted with delight and ſatisfaction, when he ſaw that all that he had done was good: And when we have ſerved our Generations by doing good, what a pleaſure will it be to reflect upon our paſt Actions? it will be a Jubilee of Joy to us, when we are going off the Stage of Life, to be aſſured we acted our parts well while we were on it.</p>
            <p>The increaſe of worldly riches increaſeth ſorrow;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135575:16"/> the pleaſures of Senſe are ſhort-liv'd, and leave a ſting behind; worldly Honour is a Wind that will either blow a Man down, or puff him up; but good Actions give a ſincere Joy, ſolid Satisfaction, and a laſting Peace: <hi>If thou draw out thy ſoul to the hungry, and ſatisfie the afflicted ſoul, then ſhall thy light riſe in obſcurity, and thy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall be as the noon-day: and the Lord ſhall guide thee continuelly, and ſatisfie thy ſoul in draught, and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt be like a watered garden, and like a ſpring of water whoſe waters fail not,</hi> Iſ. 58. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>Charity (my Honoured Country-men) is the Work of this day; it were not worth our while to meet, unleſs in order to collect for the Poor; while we feaſt, it is moſt improper to ſuffer them to ſtarve. Let us then ennoble our Society by our generous Charity, let us ſignalize our ſelves to our Fellow-Citizens by our liberal Diſtributions. Let us give to the Poor in our Health, for Charity on a dying Bed is not ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to <hi>God;</hi> it is no great Vertue to give that away, which we cannot keep any longer, or to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render that which will be taken from us by force. If we are charitable in our health, the Poor will pray for us; but if our Charity doth not commence till after Death, their Prayers are vain, and therefore cannot do us any good; let our own hands be the Executors of our Charity while we live, and then a Death-bed Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will be rendred acceptable.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider the uncertainty of all things in this World, thou who now aboundeſt, mayſt ſhortly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to want. Fortune ſtorms a loſty Caſtle, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135575:16"/> paſſeth over a low Cottage; a bluſtring Wind ſhakes the top of a tall Cedar, while the humble Shrub re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains unmov'd; an ambitious Mountain that aſpires up to Heaven, is ſooner thunder-ſtruck than the Valley. Let then the Rich ſympathize with the Miſeries of the Poor, becauſe they are ſubject to them: <hi>Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them which ſuffer adverſity, as being your ſelves alſo in the body,</hi> Heb. 13. 3.</p>
            <p>4. The happineſs of Humane Life conſiſts in a good Conſcience towards God and Man.</p>
            <p>Without Peace with God all Temporal Bleſſings are but Vanity and Vexation of Spirit; there can be no Calm within, when God is angry without; and when the Mind is uneaſie within, the whole World cannot give the leaſt Contentment. A good Conſcience crowns the Bleſſings of God with Comfort, it is the Soul's Health, and the Body's Cordial; the Salt that ſeaſons Earthly Bleſſings, and makes them reliſhable; it gives Joy in Sorrow, Comfort in Afflications, and is a hearty Friend in the Day of Adveriſity. Whether we are Rich or Poor, we can carry nothing out of the World with us, but a good or an evil Conſcience, one of thoſe will abide with us for ever. Holineſs is the life of the Soul, and a good Conſcience its proper Comfort: As he that is in Health will feed on ordinary Diet with delight, while the ſick Stomach loaths the moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Meats, ſo to a good Conſcience the worſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is pleaſant, but to an evil Conſcience all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pleaſures are but vexatious Torments.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:135575:17"/>
            <p>A good Man will be contented with much, or with little, or with nothing, becauſe he finds a full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the All-ſufficient God. Life is then happy, when we can look backward without ſhame, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward without fear, when we can expect Death with Comfort, and meet it with Courage: when we can meditate on the Terrours of Judgment, without being afraid of them, and have a ſenſe of our Reconciliation with God by Chriſt. A good Conſcience will make our Beds eaſie, and our Pillows ſoft; it will fortifie us againſt the Fears of Death and Judgment, and revive our Souls, when our Bodies languiſh under our laſt Pangs.</p>
            <p>God only, and his Grace content us in every State, God being immutably the ſame, he that enjoys him hath always enough. In all the Ebbings and Flowings of the World, a good Man is fixt upon a ſolid Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, becauſe the Object of his happineſs is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to change: <hi>Godlineſs with contentment is great gain: and godlineſs is profitable to all things, having the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the life which now is, and that which is to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 8.</p>
            <p>Let us not then ſeek Happineſs from the vain and empty World; its Pleaſures are deceitful, fugitive, and fading; its Comforts are allayed with Sorrows, its Joys are mixt with Grief, its faireſt Days have their Clouds to darken them. The World is of little uſe to the Soul while it lives in it, and of no uſe at all when it goes out of it: it is confined to the Body in this ſtate of Probation, to prepare itsſelf for a bleſſed Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135575:17"/> and then to go hence, and dwell in a World of Spirits; ſeparate Souls have no uſe of any thing that worldly Riches can purchaſe; How then do they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe their Souls who make them Slaves to their Bodies? How do they undervalue them, who give them away for the World?</p>
            <p>Time is but an Inſtant if compared with Eternity, our Lives are but a Point, if compared with the whole Line of Time; our pleaſant Hours are but a Moment, if compared with our whole Lives: What folly is it then to part with our Souls for fading things which we muſt leave when we die, and may leave before? Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things are to be uſed, not enjoyed; God is the Object of fruition, the World of uſe; the World may have our hands, God ought to have our whole hearts: <hi>But this I ſay brethren, the time is ſhort, it remaineth that both they that have wives, be as though they bad none; and they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoyce, as though they rejoyeed not; and they that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not; and they that uſe this world, as not abuſing it: for the faſhion of this world paſſeth away,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 29, 30.</p>
            <p>When the Diſciples admired to our Saviour the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificent Buildings of the Temple, he diverted them with this Conſideration: <hi>See ye not all theſe things? Verily I ſay unto you, there ſhall not be left here one ſtone upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down,</hi> Mat. 24. 2. So when we are tempted with the Riches of this World, let us fortifie ourſelves with this meditation, See ye not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135575:18"/> all theſe things? they ſhall ſhortly be found no where, but in the Aſhes of an Univerſal Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>To conclude: Let us ſeek happineſs there where only it may be found. God only is the proper ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Spirits, the Home of Souls, and the Center on whom alone they can reſt: Let us then preſent our Hearts to God, make his Will our Rule, and imitate him in holineſs; there is no true happineſs without Union with God by Faith and Love; let us then ſerve him with pure hearts, adore him with all the powers of our Souls, meditate upon him, and live to him, and then when this World ſhall be diſſolved, we ſhall have a Building of God, a Houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Heavens.</p>
            <q>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghost, Three Perſons and One Eternal God, be all Honour, Glory, Love, and Adoration, henceforth, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
